Welcome to a new information pill of your MINI ENCYCLOPEDIA OF HEALTH on the Internet.
This time we are going to explore the BINOCULAR VISION.
and how it allows us to obtain depth perception, that is, to see in 3 dimensions,
in spite of the fact that our retina is a flat tissue that collects visual information in only 2 dimensions.
This ability is possible because we do not have only one retina, but two.
Our eyes share most of their visual field, but by occupying different positions on the face,
both give us images with a slightly different angular perspective of the same scene.
Our brain is able to combine both images to obtain a single image with depth of field,
a phenomenon known as STEREOPSIS or STEREOSCOPIC VISION.
How exactly does this phenomenon occur?
In this scene we can observe how the left and right eyes are obtaining
slightly different images of the blue and red primitives and their relative positions.
The FOCUS POINT is located on the blue prism, and we can observe how its projection through the lens
is incident on anatomically corresponding areas of both retinas.
This property is not unique to the focus point,
but that all points on the arc called HOROPTER project to points anatomically
corresponding points of both retinae and can be interpreted
directly by the brain as belonging to the same perceptual object.
In addition, the brain is capable of integrating also in the same perceptual object
the projections coming from bands situated in front of and behind the HOROPTER,
forming a space known as the PANUM FUSION AREA.
Although the projections coming from this area
are not incident on anatomically corresponding points of the retina,
the brain is able to fuse them into a single image,
employing binocular disparity to obtain very accurate depth perception.
This is what lets us know that the red prism is behind the blue prism,
in a phenomenon known as QUANTITATIVE STEREOPSIS.
And what about the projections coming from OUTSIDE THE PANUM FUSION AREA?
If we place a new orange prism behind this area,
we will observe that the location of the retina on which it is projected is very different.
So much so that the brain is no longer able to fuse the two images,
and the result in a physiological diplopia, i.e. a non-pathological double vision
due to this large binocular disparity between both retinal images
This disparity is called NON-CROSSED as it is behind the horopter,
and its qualitative steropsis gives us less precise information
about deep objects with respect to the focus point.
You can reproduce this phenomenon by focusing a finger in front of your face.
and paying attention to the scene in double vision that forms behind it.
Something similar would happen by placing a green prism in front of Panum's fusion area,
again generating anatomically very dissimilar projections on each retina.
In this case, it would be a CROSSED disparity, being in front of the horopter,
and its qualitative stereopsis gives us inaccurate information about the depth of objects close to our face.
You can reproduce this phenomenon by focusing on an object far away from you.
and placing a finger in front of your face without changing the focus point.
How many fingers do you see?
Thank you very much for visiting your MINI ENCYCLOPEDIA OF HEALTH on the Internet.
We are waiting for you!